[SPEAKER_01]: there is just a very manual aspect of the program.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so while we're always looking at things to improve, I do think there would still be some responsibility that would live with the customer.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_02]: And thank you for a very clear presentation.
[SPEAKER_02]: Although I have one question of clarification.
[SPEAKER_02]: You talk about mirroring the existing service area.
[SPEAKER_02]: One of the things that appealed to me about this service was that I don't think that the customers were restricted to the three quarter mile within a fixed route.
[SPEAKER_02]: Would that change with this?
[SPEAKER_02]: Any of these proposals or would it still be over the entire RTD service area?
[SPEAKER_01]: As the pro the proposals are presented, we are proposing mirroring the three quarter of a mile boundary that exists today for our accessory customers.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay, that.
[SPEAKER_02]: That presents some problems for me, but we can talk about that later.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Secretary Nicholson.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thank you very much.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think I first want to echo and perhaps be a little bit more direct about what Director Catlin said.
[SPEAKER_00]: We have bus routes in this system that don't qualify for the ADA service, but they're bus routes anyway.
[SPEAKER_00]: There are commuter routes and I
[SPEAKER_00]: would not vote personally for a change that would cut off the people who live within three quarters of a mile of those routes.
[SPEAKER_00]: So at least for me, you guys want to get this through, you're going to need to change that because it's just a matter of basic equity.
[SPEAKER_00]: Otherwise, Peggy has like
[SPEAKER_00]: two places in our district that get service and that's just not reasonable.
[SPEAKER_00]: There are a lot of older folks that live up in those areas.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think the second issue that I have with what's being proposed is that the needs of
[SPEAKER_00]: not call it rural, but mountainous Jefferson County, when it comes to AOD are very different than the needs of central Denver.
[SPEAKER_00]: The trips I can get to most places that I need to go, in terms of grocery stores, medical, et cetera, in a $15 Uber.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't think there's anywhere that you can get to for 15 bucks in