We're convened as of 3.31 p.m. I'd respectfully ask everyone to remain
muted unless you're recognized to speak. I will now call the roll.
Treasure banker? Present. Director Buzic? I believe he's gonna be a couple minutes
late. Director Catlin? Here. Director Chandler?
Not here. Director Geisinger? Director Guchenutter? Here. Director Guzman?
Present. Director Harwick? Here. Director Larson? Here. Secretary Nicholson? Choo-choo.
First Vice Chair O'Keefe? Ecstatic to be here. Director Pagulari? Present.
Director Ruche? No. Director Ruche? Second Vice Chair Whitmore? Present.
Alright. So we have 12 present and 3 absent. We do have a quorum. Please note
that the special board meeting does have a section for public comment this
afternoon. However, the public can still offer comments, excuse me, does not have a
section for public comment this afternoon. However, the public can still offer
comments via email or by participating in person or remotely during the regular
scheduled meeting, which will be happening later this evening, either at
5.30 or potentially a little bit later, depending how long our special board
meeting happens this afternoon. Alright. So we have our external entities report
and this external entities report will be coming from the joint rail service
update. For today's special board meeting, we have just the one and today's
special guest is going to be Diane Barrett, Special Advisor to the Governor
for Joint Rail Service. Before I ask Ms. Barrett to begin, I would want to offer
the floor to GM CEO Johnson for some opening remarks. Ms. Johnson, the floor is
yours. Thank you very much, Mr. Chair. Good afternoon to all board members
assembled and those members of the public. Before we get started, just for a point
of clarification, I do know that Lisa Kaufman is present as well, Senior
Advisor to the Governor, who will be part of the presentation this afternoon. I
also like to acknowledge Ms. Elmer Hutchinson, our Deputy General Counsel,
who is sitting in today as General Counsel. And then more specifically, we
have in the audience our Chief Financial Officer, Kelly Mackey, who all formally
introduced during the course of the public board meeting. But for the matter
at hand today, as relates to the progress relative to joint service and working
with five other entities aside from, of course, ourselves with RTD and coming
forward with options relative to bringing passenger rail service to the front range
more specifically along the Northwest Corridor, we have been involved in
meetings and working diligently and our colleagues from the state are here to
provide an overview. With that as a backdrop, there'll be an opportunity
whereby this body will go into executive session and we can have a more in-depth
discussion pertinent to next steps. So with that, Mr. Chair, I would ask Ms.
Barrett and Ms. Kaufman to join us at the U-shaped table for their
presentation this afternoon. Thank you.
Ms. Barrett and Ms. Kaufman, thank you for joining us. The floor is
yours. Thank you very much. Thank you, General Manager Johnson, for that
introduction. This is my fourth appearance, I believe, with you folks. So I hope
that you're not getting bored with us. Lisa's gonna start us off and we'll go
through an overview of where we are and what we've been doing and then we'll
have a quick overview of the IGA, which you've all been looking at and thinking
about for a while and then that'll be it and questions. Great, thanks Diane. So I'll
get an overview on where we've been to date and what the overall timeline for
the project is. So some background is SB 184 was signed into law May of 2024
and in this new law it created a new congestion fee of three dollars a day on
daily rental cars, which is estimated to bring in a new 57 million dollars in FY
26 before growing to over a hundred and ten million dollars by 2050 and in that
law it directed RTD front-range passenger rail and CDOT to collaborate
to deliver on starter service for inner-city passenger rail from Denver to
Fort Collins by January 2029. It allowed the entities to contemplate three
different ways to govern this collaborative to deliver passenger rail
through either an IGA or a new Colorado Rail Authority or an altogether new
legal authority and what the principals kind of rallied around early on was the
concept of an IGA given that all the existing entities had the legal
authority they needed to govern the service and enter into the service
through an IGA. I would say that some previous board members from RTD during
the process of this legislation were advocates for the new Colorado Rail
Authority as a potential solution and that idea still has some merit but the
legislation did not create an appropriation to do a proper study on
that concept so early on that concept was really only given a cursory look as
it's a complicated endeavor that would have needed in appropriation to do a
full analysis on that concept so it's just worth noting it's not that the
principals decided that concept was without merit it just was something that
would have needed far more resources to really explore that as a viable
governance option. Also in last year's legislative session SP 230 passed which
is a new production fee on oil and gas extraction. This law is forecasted in its
first full year to bring in around a hundred and ten million dollars. The
lion's share beneficiary will likely be RTD as 70% of it is to go out to local
transit agencies for increasing service and ridership that is to go out
formulaically 70% of it and then there is a 20% set aside for passenger rail
that calls out prioritization for completion of the Northwest rail and the
end line. This is a project overview for the work around joint service so as I
just went through May 2024 SP 184 and SP 230 was signed into law. In August of
2024 the principals of joint service met so general managers from RTD, FRPRD,
Director Liu and the governor and decided to bring on the ever talented
Diane Barrett to help lead that this project and lead the interagency
coordination. You know part of the reason why the principals decided to bring on
Diane is that one of the most successful collaboratives that the state of Colorado
has seen was the renovation and revitalization of Union Station which
required a lot of coordination among many different public entities to come
together to come up with the creative financing mechanism to get that done and
Diane led that project for then Mayor Hickenlooper as the first chief project
officer and so we're very blessed for her to come out of retirement to come
lead this and do it again because it is a Herculean effort to coordinate this
many public entities with their own policies bylaws and enabling legislation
and so there really is truly no one better to do this work than Diane which
then led to the March 1st report that had an initial cost estimate in review
of available revenue streams and review of governance models and so we'll review
a little bit of what the March 1st report said but in you know succinctly
it said that there is enough existing resources and that an IGA is the
preferred governance model to deliver joint service. We have since spent the
time since March 1st refining the study and looking at updating the cost
estimates based off of the feedback from the March 1st report based off of
additional feedback from BNSF and drafting the IGA and doing workshops
like we are here today with the governing boards. So the drafting of the
IGA has been led by Diane but also the general counsels from RTD, FRPRD and
the attorney general's office and we have now done workshops including today
with all the governing boards we expect that feedback from all of the workshops
and the ongoing drafting will continue until about mid-June in which we hope to
be able to circulate a final draft in mid-June for board adoptions this summer
in June and July.
So this is a project timeline moving forward and kind of gets at the heart of
what is the IGA about but final steps as I said is to circulate a final draft of
the IGA in June and then start operating under the governance of the IGA to
speak with one voice in negotiations with BNSF with the hope of getting an
access agreement with BNSF and be able to then have a finance model based off
of the actual cost based off of the actual infrastructure list negotiated
with BNSF and that at that point we would then be asking for boards to adopt
financial plans based off of the actual negotiations with BNSF and that that
would then kick off kind of the procurement for operator and executing of
financing any NEPA's that are needed construction and safety testing with the
commencement of service in January 2029. One thing I would say about this is I
was just the state's chief negotiator for the Union Pacific Access Agreement for
Mountain Rail which was a good learning experience to understand how those
documents answer a lot of the questions that I'm sure you all have on how is the
infrastructure cost associated with this determined what's the timeline who does
the work how is it going to proceed and so that access agreement is foundational
to any project for passenger rail and what we have heard loud and clear from
BNSF is that the need for joint service is because right now absent having an IGA
that says we're going to deliver passenger rail on the northern sub
collaboratively there is multiple different public agencies that are
planning passenger rail projects on the northern sub that they own from
Denver Union Station to Fort Collins and that if those projects were to proceed
in a silo that adds a level of complexity and conflict with freight
operations that would have a cost estimate impact to all projects so to
put that more succinctly if Front Range passenger rail were to price out their
project right now BNSF would assume the infrastructure needs for Northwest Rail
in addition to Front Range passenger rail which would balloon the cost for Front
Range passenger rail as there are multiple passenger rail systems planned
and so the interagency agreement is designed to really say that the public
agencies are going to work together to get one access agreement and have one
operator to create that efficiencies for both the taxpayer and fee payers that
would be funding the service but also to reduce any conflict with freight
operations both from a safety perspective but also from a freight
business perspective and so the goal of the IGA is to say this is how we will
work together here's the core principles of the collaborative and be able to go
speak with one voice in those negotiations with BNSF so that we can
get the most cost-efficient passenger rail system on the northern Front Range
that I think I turn it over to Diane to go over key takeaways from the March
1st report
thank you Lisa
from the March 1st report we or by the time of the March 1st report we had
learned that there are enough existing resources from the concession impact fee
and the production fee in SB 184 and SB 230 and RTD's sales tax to cover the
cost of three daily round trips remember that we were asked to look at three and
five round trips any appropriation made by any of the parties ie the agencies is
subject to policy and decision budget decisions of the governing boards
something for you all specifically to keep in mind general manager Johnson will
be coming to you for your prior approval before any action is is taken three
daily round trips is estimated to cost 83 million dollars in the first year of
operations 32 million of that is O&M plus 51 million in debt service we will
be updating those numbers which are the same numbers you saw the last two times
I was here I believe we'll be updating those in the next coming weeks and in
our June presentation to you we will have very interesting new numbers to show
you if the state contributes 42 million dollars annually from 230 and 184
numbers there is a gap of 41 million dollars to be filled by RTD
the peak rail study that you folks did at great costs recently and by the way we
are using data from that report constantly it's been a tremendous boom
to joint service to have that study in place so you should be proud of that
anyway three trains from Denver to only to Longmont is said to be 52 to 56
million dollars annually for you by yourselves so 41 million is
significantly less than that and the service would be connecting twice than
an amount of population that would be going to Fort Collins rather than just
to Longmont nearly all of the infrastructure investments for the joint
service that we're planning would benefit the eventual front-range passenger rail
further study is needed to define the service negotiate an access agreement
with BNSF develop an internet agency agreement and importantly a financial
plan that will work
why did we decide to do an intergovernmental agreement the
remaining choice as you heard from Lisa earlier was really establishing a new
entity a new public entity that's what we did in Denver Union Station and we did
it there for various reasons it was kind of a first shot out of the box and we
did it Ms. Catlin sat on our original board so we did we did feel that after
the fact probably could have done it with an IGA it was a big complication
but we decided in this instance that the agencies were familiar enough with each
other that we could probably do this with an intergovernmental agreement less
expense less time and we think that we will have a binding agreement that can
be to everybody's benefit so we decided that we would have the
collaboration that we need and be able to establish a governance process we
didn't really need a lot more than that to get started so remember what we're
doing is a starter service so the IGA creates a Joint Service Executive
Oversight Committee JSEOC that acts on behalf of the group and remember that
the group is the executives of each of the agencies so the group is General
Manager Johnson it's hard not to say Debra sorry and our president
actually the executives are the voting body that I'm sorry I'm thinking of our
principles meetings in which you attend and so does the board chair of FRPRD but
the voting members of the JSEOC are General Manager Johnson interim general
manager Chrissy Bright at FRPRD the executive of CTIO the executive of CTE
and Shoshana Liu or her delicate and the governor or his which is Lisa
the JSEOC becomes the single entity that BNSF has been asking for all along he
wants one neck to choke I guess way that you can think about that
the IGA does not supersede or impact the authority of any body so all of the
boards act just as they always have you will continue to have the control that
you want and need in order to fulfill your obligations fiduciary and otherwise
the boards will make all decisions regarding appropriations budgeting
funding unless those decisions have been expressly dedicated by the individual
governing body to someone for instance your general manager
it is expected that the JSEOC will make the decisions that they make by a
measure of 50 percent plus one which so you don't have to do the arithmetic is a
vote of four to prevail upon an adoption of the financial plan and this is at the
end of at the conclusion of a successful negotiation with BNSF when we have
learned what the real costs are of this project and we have learned how big your
financial contributions will be and that financial plan will be adopted and after
that all voting will be majority just a majority vote unless and until one person
or more than one choose to ask for a weighted vote this is not a sure thing
but today we are still carrying a weighted vote opportunity after the
adoption of the financial plan if one of the members asks for a weighted vote
that will happen and it the waiting is as of the contributions of the parties
and contributions of course will be carefully carefully defined and is still
a very open definition in the documents
so
so sorry thank you Lisa the JSEOC will steer the negotiations with BNSF will be
responsible for soliciting an operator for the passenger rail service and they
will be laying the foundation for the future expansion of the Front Range
passenger district the JSEOC will strive to implement the joint service project
in such a way that it will not render infeasible the existing operations of
RTD or the future plans for the Front Range passenger rail district that
sounds very legal and a little bit hard to operate with so we're looking at that
language and trying hard to come up with a language that will assure that the
Front Range passenger rail is not impeded in the future by what we're doing
with our project with the small starter small project that we're working on
today the IGA also provides a process for transfer of interests assets and
obligations of one of the parties to others or to outsiders as well this is a
process that again is still under discussion and redrafting to try to make
it a fair way to transfer if trans such transfer is wanted it actually is
important in order to assure that in the in the event of a need to break up the
partnership we have a orderly process in place that will help that happen there
are many instances of large groups of participants who end up not being able
to make work and it's best to have a process in place in the original
agreement if possible
so our timeline in May just barely we managed to get the workshops all done
with parties in June we'll do another RTD board update and that one will in
entail some specificity about dollars and cents that we don't have quite yet
and certainly it will lead us on the pathway to negotiations with BNSF which
obviously have to occur and conclude before we will know what the financial
picture really is and adopt a financial plan for the project June and July the
boards begin voting and approving the IGA so in June the CTIO the CTE and the
Transportation Commission will all have their opportunity to approve to approve
the IGA in June the FRPRD will have their opportunity to approve the IGA and
then in July you folks will have your opportunity to do the same you get to
be last through the winter all the boards will work to adopt the financial
plan again it would be negotiations with the NSF are critical and key here and
those have to be ongoing and we hope that during the winter all the boards
will be able to adopt a financial plan that's based on the successful access
agreement and construction agreements that we've achieved with the NSF the
summer of next year the JSEOC will conduct procurement for rolling stock
and for the operator and then in January of 2029 joint service train begins
that's you know tomorrow in the rain in the train world so optimistic aggressive
yes just real quick as a correction miss Barrett it says winner of 2026 on there
I believe it is winner of 2025 all boards to adopt financial plan yes could
expand the year 26 in January okay thank you
but hopefully hopefully thank you chairman bouquet so in the June board
update what will I do just another boring turnout but we'll have sent out
the finalized IGA draft on all board workshops the new cost estimate by H&T B
will be presented very interesting we have looked in all the couch covers and
we have found many pennies so we are we're going to be showing to you some
new numbers there will be a new financial scenario based on those new
cost estimates and this time will include Fairbox collections because we
will have ridership scenarios by that time for you which I'm sure will be very
interested all of you the ridership model is completed and we'll be able to
present it to you and then we'll have an operations report that will provide
analyses financially and operationally to date so I believe that that's it for
our report and we'd be pleased to take your question excellent well thank you
both for coming in and joining us again we greatly appreciate and greatly
appreciate your guys's time so now I'm gonna leave it up to the board if they
have any questions for the two of you so there any directors who have questions
treasure Banker well first of all thank you for coming again we you've been
doing yeoman's work here and providing leadership on this project which is
extremely valuable and appreciated I do have a couple of questions actually I've
got many I'll keep it short though when you talk about a weighted vote for this
joint operating agreement could you give me an example how would that work
well Lisa chip in afterwards a weighted vote would give more weight to to a vote
by a party that has contributed more than another party so the definition of
contributions is being heavily debated among the council guided by their
principles of course and and there are lots of different ideas about how to do
that for instance we had in one draft the specifics of the peak rail study as
having been an expenditure that RTD would get credited with because it was
huge amount of money I think eight million dollars or something like that
as you all know better than I do and the BNSF study so wanting to make sure
that that was included in contributions and it was suggested I think from from
your counsel and we were talking about it behind the scenes and we said well
you know we don't want everybody putting in every example of every time they've
spent money and so forth and so we'll just say by exam we won't say by example
we'll just say here's the definition of what a contribution is it became clear
to us that we specifically wanted to delineate the peak study because a it
was unique among other studies and expenditures that people have have made
but we still don't want to enumerate every single expenditure but we're going
to put that one in specifically because it was large and it was important
throughout our studies and will continue to be so contributions is a financial
contribution that again will the the definition will be further refined as we
talk more mr. chair if I if I could continue then how would you something to
think about you don't have to answer it right now but they're very well maybe
one-time contributions that are made as well as annual contributions that are
made so however that is calculated hopefully that is taken into
consideration well the amounts right total and in integrate integral would be
heavily a part of the amount itself is a very important part of the analysis okay
and then one more question then if you don't mind yeah treasure a total
contribution director banker a total contribution would be even if you were
paying it over time it was the total contribution would be what you would be
so if there was a bond then you would calculate the 30-year payment of a bond
as well as one-time deposit yes say at the beginning of the project yes okay
interesting you had mentioned that you're talking between three and five
trips a day how are you where are we in the potential of five trips
I'm gonna ask Lisa to take that one yeah so I think there was an updated cost
estimate that looked at the five round trips and I think that it's really kind
of on the bubble if there is enough existing resources at this point to
pursue five round trips and so we've really been focusing on the three daily
round trips it's also been you know an active dialogue with BNSF and they
certainly would prefer that any interagency agreement be prioritizing
starting off at two to three round trips with the you know expectation that you
would increase frequency as new resources became available and as the
service was successful in operating on their line with the existing
infrastructure dictated in the access agreement and so it's not envisioned
that you would end without amount of frequency but that that's where you your
starting point is and as you might know FRPRD is currently doing open open
houses and workshops on their alternative analysis and part of the
alternative analysis for front-range passenger rail is a benchmark study of
all inner-city passenger rail services in the country and what they looked at
was where do they start and where do they kind of top out and what you find
is a lot start with two to three round trips and then the kind of high level is
you know between 12 and 16 round trips for inner city passenger rail and so
that is kind of the range in which we would expect to try to reach eventually
with our ridership demand being built up and with added capacity on the line to
accommodate new frequency is certainly all the state's hope that front-range
passenger rail eventually goes to the ballot and is successful so that we can
increase frequency with new resources that they bring to the table. Thank you
treasurer. Prior to recognizing first vice chair O'Keeffe I do want to make I do
want to make note that at around 340 director Buza and director Usha did
join us online thank you first vice chair O'Keeffe. Thank you
mr. chair and I will note that director Buza put his hand up as soon as he got
on the call he didn't even know what we were debating at this time so you know
what they call going to the same body four times and not getting what they call
the body that you go to four times and they don't get this don't get a yes
parole board so you're coming to the parole board so the a couple things that
actually the previous question we think of it is there a minimum contribution is
it's of an entity doesn't give any money or do they get no vote when you go to a
waiting boat okay yeah I'm not generally quiet so so could you repeat that real
quick explain explain how that for the recording that would work I'm sorry how
would that work so if you if you're pro rate if you're pro rating out based on
contribution but there are entities that don't give anything do you give them they
get a minimum like 10% vote or what's the idea on the waiting and it it will
matter more in construction right so I mean I'm particularly interested in if
we're gonna wait waiting it correctly well and and that's why we're struggling
with the language of both the definition of definite of contributions and with
how the actual weighted works so there is no there is no thought of taking away a
vote so each of the six has a vote and for most most actions that will be taken
everybody's vote will be the same after the the adoption of the finance plan and
when we're actually you know creating a project that has a cost and a budget and
is sticking with all of that then then most votes will be one vote one person
but if we have to go to a weighted vote the amount of
votes will increase by the contribution level okay can I maybe jump in with an
example of this so I think that the current way the IGA has contemplated is
the bodies would govern with 50% plus one and that would be you know the
governing rules through negotiations with BNSF to get to an access agreement
then a finance plan would come out of the access agreement based off of
actually having an infrastructure project list and more solid numbers an
instance in where you might want a weighted vote is you know say the
services and operation for three years and we think that it's worth having a
discussion on adding a siding because it might improve performance and you know
being on time performance you would presume that the entities would then
vote through 50% plus one but somebody could ask for a weighted vote on that
decision based off of contributions it's designed to give an added layer of
protection for the entities that are contributing large amounts but of course
there's another layer of protection for the agencies that are contributing to
the service because all of those appropriations still have to be
appropriated by the originating board and nobody could be forced by the
interagency agreement to appropriate any money for the service and so it's just
an added layer of protection for the entities that have the most equity into
the service okay but I think that the practice what we expect to see is that
the majority rule would be how decisions are made I would hope so but if you need
to go to a weighted vote things aren't going well so I think you may want to
war game out how that would would work and so just a couple things can we get a
copy of the idea I I've asked just about everybody I almost asked a guy out on the
street I might have it so I looked at general manager Johnson but my
understanding was that the general counsels for each agency was sharing
with their governing boards to protect client privilege so I don't know where
that may be got lost in translation but that's how we've done it at least in the
executive branch where each Attorney General assigned to each agency has
shared it with those boards that's perfect she did she just gave me the
answer with her she didn't even have to leer at me the so the only other things
and I just I think this is important to at least start talking about in the
context the IGA I understand the IGA is not designed to set a budget request but
I do think it should set parameters that that under no circumstances aboard would
support that's so we have to decide voting ourselves what is something we
would know would not accept and I'll give you two examples that I will
specifically ask for first who's the backstop if it goes over if I know it'll
shock people for me to think that a rail project might be over budget but just in
case we found one that does who pays and at what at what percentage because and I
think that's really important going into negotiations with BNSF because that's
gonna be your biggest expenditure and they need to people should know their
negotiating position before they go in with BNSF and I think that's that helps
the negotiators it's it's also helpful that the board say look under no
circumstances and with a backstop we will give you the amount of money in the
agreement and no more or we will give you more and this is what our percentage
looks like it's I think that's really really important the second thing is and
this is this is a like a cut-and-dry issue for me under no circumstances can
all the fights and money go to this project there are several unfinished
projects in fast tracks and there are a lot of disappointed voters and I'm not
saying it has to be counted out percentage-wise to the penny there
certainly could be greater weighting to this project because it actually has a
greater chance of going forward but under no circumstances would I vote for
anything that is takes the vast honor into the FISA money because I probably
wouldn't make it back across the Douglas County line alive so that's just I think
those parameters that we can start to stake out for you before we vote would
be really helpful so the negotiators aren't left in a tough position sorry
mr. chair can I react to that so the goal would be that the access agreement
would have an infrastructure list that corresponds with you know the daily
round trips right so it might be that for instance if you want it five daily
round trips that that would require seven new sightings and then what the
finance plan would then say is here are the sightings that are needed in order
to accommodate the five daily round trips here are the ones that are in the
RTD region here are the ones that are out and then that finance plan would be
what came back you know next winter to say here's kind of the pieces of who's
gonna finance what and then to your point then if any one project goes over
what does that look like and how do you handle any overages but it would be what
our anticipation based off of the current cost estimates right is if we're
negotiating for two or three daily round trips with them is that there is that
infrastructure cost associated with it we have some ideas of what those are
based off of the RTC modeling that was done ahead of the March 1st report and
the RTC model is based off of the business data provided under an NDA from
BNSF so it's a very informed cost estimate what is coming back to you in
June is since then we've gotten we passed review at the FRA under the new
administration for the Chrissy Grant so we know that those costs are going to be
covered now through that Chrissy Grant so those kind of refinements is coming
back but but really that finance plan has to be based off of the actual
agreement with BNSF for the actual projects and then understanding how that
each one of those gets financed is what we anticipate yeah I appreciate all that
that really helps the the I guess the the challenge is there's a there's a
finite amount that we would chip in and I don't know what that is yet yeah but
that would be the only money coming from this body I don't think that there's I
mean I get almost get an informal vote right now that we would enter an
agreement where we did not know what our obligation was and and and did not know
who was responsible when we exceeded that that original budget it might be us
that's fine but we need to delineate who who's what and the the railroad
negotiation will be murkier than we want this
miss Barrett and I have done one railroad negotiation before and they
everything is tied together in some sort of safety plan they rarely will say this
siding is the responsibility of this customer it's all they're very good at
creating a mismatch of of requirements and costs in fact they're experts at it
yeah I would say that our hope is that it's enumerated in the agreement and in
the mountain rail access agreement that we just completed on May 1st it is all
enumerate it for the project by segment in which phase that you run does it
trigger the need for that infrastructure so I think our hope is that we would be
able to accomplish that same sort of format that we just did I would say on
your other feedback on on finished fast tracks projects I mean I think that it's
hopefully clear to all if not maybe worth stating that certainly we would
like to partner to finish all of them and to bring state resources to partner
to finish all of them it is called out in Senate bill SB 230 that the rail set
aside is for both Northwest rail and the end line and I think that the hope is
that we can get some clarity on where the communities are on the Southwest
extension and the Five Points Project to understand how the state could also
partner on those so it's probably worth me stating that on the mic is that the
state wants to partner to finish all on finished fast-tracks projects as we see
this out there as a threat to voter confidence for us to get to where we
want to go on our climate goals thank you first vice chair Keith director
of music thank you very much and again thank you to miss pop in and despair it
for once again coming in and giving us an update but one question and two
comments and my first the question has to do with SB 230 and that set aside the
20 percent set aside for Northwest rail and the end line and I just don't
remember does the legislation determine the proportion that those lines share
that 20 percent or not anybody can answer that that might know it does not
it just calls out prioritizing that 20 percent set aside for those two projects
and so in the first report what we did was for just the exercise of trying to
identify is there enough unallocated resources to cover the cost was to just
assume a 50/50 split but that is a decision that the clean transit
enterprise board needs to make okay so that's the the entity that would make
that decision okay yeah I just would not want to see the end line swept away to
to put all the money into this project so the other comments and it's been
touched on and I have more things but I'll bring this up in executive session
I think it's more appropriate for that but the access agreement BNS BNSF it
are you gonna negotiate the cost of increased frequency because I can see
them saying listen when you guys are ready to go to nine or ten or twelve
trips a day come on back in and we'll talk and then then they've got you so
hopefully we can get some incremental increase amounts or prices or cost
worked into that access agreement because I can see that coming back to
bite us if we don't and last but not least I mentioned all along you know we
did that the peak service rail study and the per rider subsidy number scary so
hopefully now I've heard allusion to basically doubling population that this
line can serve and hopefully with that we'll bring that number down I'm still
hoping to see an update on ridership projections on this whole line and what
that does to the provider subsidy and that's all I have for now but I'm I'm
looking forward to it I said it once I said it again this is the only way we're
getting rail up there and I hope we do it so thanks a lot thank you director one
thing I would just react to of the overall cost per rider and you know this
is an unfortunate fact for this line but the single biggest infrastructure cost
for this line is to add positive train control from Westminster to Fort
Collins and this is a basic safety system that you would hope was on an
existing freight line that is moving you know all sorts of petrochemicals and
hazardous on freight through our northern suburbs today but it's not
mandated for them to move those free products today it's only mandated when
you add passenger rail onto the line and so when you look at the cost a lot of it
is driven by the need for positive train control which is a significant
improvement to safety for those communities that I would love to see
today but it's regulated at the federal level we can't regulate it at the state
level it is a big part of the Christie grant is extending positive train
control up to Broomfield and it's a service I think to safety to all of us
to invest in getting positive train control on this line for freight
operations which is why we were able to successfully partner with BNSF to get
that Christie grant and the way that that worked was we took the engineering work
and the study done through the peak rail study and we were able to utilize that
engineering work in order to put in a Christie grant that was you know close
to shove that shovel ready so it's a great return on your investment for peak
rail that we were able to secure over 90 million dollars investment that is a
safety feature that is needed today whether or not we ever put a passenger
on it so it's a little bit of a misnomer when you look at the cost that we're
kind of bearing the full cost of needing a basic safety feature that we should
all want to have on there today for freight operations thank you director
Catlin thank you and I have I have a lot of questions the I met five years ago
along with our engineering staff down in Fort Worth with the BNSF and at that
time and to director O'Keefe's point with the railroads it's a moving target and
have they reviewed these costs independently that's question number one
so they've seen our presentation they haven't done a verification process but
they also agree directionally with where we've been on our cost I think that they
would say is you know through negotiations if we were willing to agree
with a lower frequency for starting that the cost could actually probably go
further down than where we are today but that is for negotiations with them you
brought up a good point I just know that when we when we were talking about the
peak rail study we had to pay the railroad for them to do the cross
estimate and so I just wanted the board to be aware of that the next thing when
you talk about increased frequencies and I remember that was a sticking point
during those preliminary discussions there has to be a ceiling I mean they're
beyond which their operations couldn't support additional frequencies and has
that been discussed or called out
I think that there's a ceiling before you get to having to double track
significant mileage is maybe what you're asking and I think this is included in
the full build out for Front Range passenger rails alternative analysis that
kind of goes through based off of the RTC modeling done for them when you trigger
additional sightings or double tracking needed so that is in the service
development plan for Front Range passenger rail and it's based off of BNSF's
business data both for operations today and their forecasted operations for the
future so this was something that was a new process really came out of you know
kind of the missteps of California high-speed rail of not really having
this modeling done on the front end and also not having the business case for
rail operations done on the front end and really just waiting for a NEPA
process before you get to any of those processes so when IJ passed they
created this new process for these service development plans that is a
federal document that goes through each step of this that Front Range passenger
rail is currently doing and we're actually the first rail project in the
country that is this far ahead with it and so there was a period of time where
we were stalled a little bit because we were the first to enter into NDA's with
the class 1 railroads to get their business data in to inform our RTC
modeling and that is now we have the the NDA is done the RTC modeling is
undergoing for all those increased frequencies and RTC model then tells you
what all the infrastructure improvements are based off of those
frequencies. Well good I want to say that they're usually pretty stingy with their
data so could you offer for getting that took a while you brought something else
up and that's the NEPA process and pardon me I'm dusting off the cobwebs
from years ago but there's a process for approving fixed rail in through the Dr.
Cobb process I think it's called Senate bill 208 is that right okay and are we
going to be needing to go through that process for this as well even though the
project limits extend beyond the Dr. Cobb region? You know it's a good
question that I don't have a complete resolution on we have had conversations
with Dr. Cobb leadership on this and they aren't clear either if this project
would be subject to it I believe Northwest rail has already been approved
by them and is there underlying as part of fast tracks it was right and so it's
unclear because this is you know a slight modification and it extends beyond their
borders so it is an outstanding question I have into the Attorney General's office
on it and you know maybe we need some cleanup legislation to clarify that too
it just needs some clarity on it I think yep but thank you all for your hard
work I'm sure we'll have more questions as time goes on but I appreciate it thank
you. Thank You director Catlin I have three directors in the queue I have
secretary Nicholson next thank you very much chair bouquet I actually have a
question for staff before I ask questions of our lovely guests and the
first the question is I know there's a provision either in the RTD Act or in
our bylaws that requires a super majority of the board to approve any new
rail projects is my understanding so would this require the the eventual
agreement would that require ten votes from us or would it only require eight
votes from us? Miss Johnson yes thank you very much secretary Nicholson for the
question I believe general counsel Snyder issued an opinion on that
previously and so we will recirculate that document thank you okay appreciate
that the second so now switching over to our wonderful guests I have two
questions the first one given that this service doesn't happen without RTD's
substantial financial contribution why shouldn't we get a veto over any JSEOC
decision if you eventually need to get our approval and our money to make this
happen well I think you essentially do because it still has to originate from
you appropriating monies or entering into any contract that RTD would enter
into what the Joint Executive Committee would do would be kind of the day-to-day
manager of the negotiations with BNSF or any day-to-day management of a selected
operator but you know any major decision that impacted the ability to actually
implement the project would still have to be decided upon by the RTD board
thanks yeah to be clear I was talking about the veto by our person on the JSEOC
over a decision by the JSEOC because again without our 40 million a year or
whatever it ends up being you guys the train doesn't happen was essentially my
question and I guess I'll just leave that out there second question forgive me
for this there's an internet meme about a relationship between a man and a woman
in a relationship about to be intimate and the caption reads aren't you
forgetting someone with a picture of Jesus off to the side I mentioned this
because reading over the timeline there's a lot of mentions of RTD and CTIO
and the governor but it seems like there's no time built in after the
finalization of the financial plan to go to the public and ask the voters and
talk to the voters and present to the voters about what we're doing what it
costs and why we should do it in the first place so my question to you is
basically why shouldn't we bake in time to do a real road show of this project
why shouldn't the governor go to places and present on this train that he wants
why shouldn't we go and present on these things before we take a massive history
defining vote on this item and allocate hundreds of millions of dollars of the
public's money it seems like you don't want that to happen or you would have
put time for it in the schedule and I'm curious whether I'm reading that
correctly thanks yeah I would say that throughout this whole process we are
doing significant public engagement I know I personally do you know a lot of
presentations to a lot of different community members so presenting to city
councils along the corridor the general public so there is inherently baked into
the project a lot of community engagement it's just not enumerated in
these slides these slides were more of an overview of what the project is but I
would also say that you know clearly the public has voted in fast-tracks in '04
they voted when they elected their representatives in the General Assembly
that passed these bills and there is inherent built into this community
engagement that we just didn't add to the slides but we certainly can give you a
report on all of the public engagement to date it's actually a pretty long
section in the March 1st report on all the community engagement that
happened in the lead up to the March 1st report I would anticipate we would have
a similar one in the June report yeah and actually there was one in the 30
September as well so all the reports that we've put out and the one that we
would is coming contain lists of who we've talked to and generally speaking
in in what venues secretary just very quickly I mean I'm a pretty engaged guy
in Denver in in central Denver have you guys done any presentations public
presentations in my district have you done any kind of you know when we've
done big changes when we talked about BRT we do big Roadhouse presentations we
bring the public in you know it's in the news it's on our website I read the post
practically every day most of my friends do I go on reddit on a regular basis
answer questions there I haven't seen you guys on there I haven't seen
literally any big public events about this project explaining it to people
I've seen one article about hey this is coming the trains coming sooner than you
expected it would that's all anybody in my district knows about this at this
point and I'll just be honest I don't see myself even if I like the project I
don't see myself voting for it unless I think that you guys your boss has done
the work necessary to sell this to the public and to sell this to the people
who are here now not necessarily the people who are here when I wasn't
legally able to drink thanks Thank You secretary director Geisinger thank you
and thank you both for all your work and and all the team I agree with director
Buzwick this is the way to get to get this service done and this starter
service I have a couple questions you mentioned that 42 million would be
coming from the state does how does that come is it is the the 230 money come out
of CTE and how much is that and the CTIO then put in I mean is that a is that a
total of several different contributions from those different groups yeah that is
a total of several different contributions and so I think it would be
a mixture of CTIO investing in the projects that the construction projects
that they would invest in finance and probably oversee the execution of same
thing for CTE and then the you know in the March 1st report we weren't sure if
the Chrissy Grant projects would get done because they were under review of
the new administration that has since been greenlighted by the new
administration and so that would probably be a new contribution that would
be reflected in the mixture of contributions and those monies came from
the governor's IJ cash fund to match the federal funds good thanks and just one
other comment which is that I think this happened in in one of the statues 161
161 yeah but I think that joint service talking about being Northwest Rail is
confusing and maybe it's better to maybe the language is important that it's
service on the Northwest Corridor to sort of pull apart Northwest Rail was
defined in you know fast tracks project and so it's just a thought and maybe
something we can we can talk about after we see the IGA and all of that thank you
very much Diane did you have something there you look like you were going to
respond I was just gonna say that the statute uses Northwest fixed guideway
thank you director guys here director Risha
thank you mr. chair so as usual director Catlin got to a question before I did
and I I just wanted to offer that I had up until this moment always assumed that
dr. Krog would need to be involved because of just a plain language reading
of statute so I would also add that if we need to clarify that we should do that
as soon as practicable which would be next session but I I also I feel like I
owed the you and my colleagues that just honesty that my district best tracks is
not something I hear about in my district nor is this project I've been on the
board for two and a half years and I think I have been asked about it less
than ten times and half of them were from reporters to be to be honest and so
I have some concern that proponents of the project aren't doing the necessary
work in my district which is very active in local matters to get their buy-in and
even if we move forward without FRPR having statutory authority to tax
because it was granted by the voters or you know we have some sort of
alternative method at the end of the day we are going to be held responsible by
the larger public and it's really crucial to ensure that we have their
buy-in so the feedback I gave was anecdotal that's just my experience but
I I I would I would feel irresponsible if I if I didn't put that out there because
it really does worry me that we might be getting married without a prenup or
we're moving too quickly but we don't have public buy-in so just like in other
parts of RTD where the fact that this these projects were not finished creates
distrust we have to remember that not all parts of the district or the greater
region share that sentiment and we just need to be careful and how we move
forward because at the end of the day no matter what happens in this board room
or the state level or the executive level we are ultimately going to respond
to the taxpayers I I would like to see this project and all rail projects get
built out I don't like cars and I don't like concrete jungles I I have concerns
about the fiscal aspect that I think first vice jiro Keith summed up much
more eloquently than I could but I would like to think it's possible so I'm
looking for a reason to say yes and I just need a little bit more to get there
and that's a bit painful to say in a public meeting with my colleagues but
at this juncture it doesn't do any of us any good if we are not forthright in
where we are so thank you for for letting me speak and that concludes my
comments thank you director Risha I have director Guzman next thank you mr.
chair I have to second first vice chair O'Keefe there's absolutely no way I
would vote for this if we're gonna just completely empty out what everybody
perceives to be the big piggy bank the price account that 190 million is not
just for rail as has been purported and reported and rereported incorrectly there
were caveats with that money for how it was to be used in conjunction with the
fast-tracks plans and I think that we need to go back to the legislation and
look at that also the five second was created after the point zero four percent
sales and use tax was collected and there are additional monies that are in
there that are also not directly linked to that legislation and so untangling
that could be a big mess but also we need to be responsible with it as is our
fiduciary duty it does support service services along the Northwest Corridor
not just the fixed rail but also other other bus services and connections that
were part of the anticipated cost of moving people around and it supports the
maintenance and the transit asset management along that rail and so one
thing that I have not heard come out of these conversations that is going to be
it's going to keep me on the no side until I understand it in terms of an IGA
is how we are going to plan the trusset transit asset management piece of this
how are we going to do maintenance and repair work because the cost of a shiny
new thing is one thing but maintaining it to continue good usage and safety for
the public is a completely different matter and we have just spent the last
two summers I'm gonna include the current one we're walking into now doing
exactly that work because it was forgotten for more than 20 years and it
cannot happen with this project so if money is not set aside or anticipated
with all the glory of putting a brand new shiny train on a track to get people
moving and continue to maintain that asset by all members of the IGA
absolutely not there's no way we can continue forward with the conversation
it's not even worth having so if that money is not accounted for somewhere in
the finance planning of doing this there's no way we would do it and why do
I say that because safety has to come first human lives are at risk and a
danger so as you spoke to the positive train control and all of the other
necessary infrastructure to do this maintenance of these tracks and these
conveyances are going to be equally important and should not be put to the
side in a rush to get a train on a track that's not how we do things and that's
not how we should do things in my opinion so that's one part sorry my
comment the other thing is we I have a big concern about cannibalizing our
regular service when the language that you put on the screen earlier says we
will I believe it was will strive to implement the joint service plan that
will not render infeasible the existing operations of RTD from or for from or
the future plans for FRPRD we are running an active transit agency we have
services going we collect a sales and use tax of a total of 1% 0.1% but it's
divided in how we use it with funds being restricted to certain aspects of
it that is where we have to consider how we are going to as a body put money into
this and where it's going to come from but the backstop question is super
important because the backstop if it falls to us to fix the matters that are
overrun on finances can literally cut bus service jobs and take away the things
that we are currently providing and that would not be fair for a three round trip
a day service to one particular area of the region because it doesn't take into
consideration everybody's need to move around our entire region that's all I
have thank you thank you director Guzman director Harwick I have a like a few
questions and thoughts but the first question is you reference 83 million for
the first year of operations 32 for operations maintenance 51 in debt service
with that 51 million in mind what is the amount of debt I just if you could
remind me what's the amount of debt that you anticipate taking on
so the March 1st report is that study so it's looking at how much would it cost
in current borrowing to finance the full 885 and that's where you get a debt
payment number of 51 million dollars annually to finance the full 885 in
regards to director Guzman's comments I think it's also important to remember in
the March 1st report that when you look at the full horizon of the project there
is baked into the underlying cost assumption the state of good repair and
safety ongoing cost and so you probably don't remember the bars from the last
presentation but it's in there in those outer years when you have to start
replacing and doing the state of good repair work and what was important about
the March 1st report is really looking at not just is there enough existing
revenue today but is there enough existing revenue to through 2050 and so
the report that Ernst & Young created for us was to look at all of the revenue
sources and to look at their growth trajectory to make sure that they also
track with the growth trajectory of the state of good repair and escalating
costs for the service and so in that March 1st report that you all got it did
do that work and you know where I showed you today that the daily rental car fee
grows from 57 million dollars in 2026 and grows to 110 million dollars in 2050
a similar number was in the March 1st presentation to you all of looking at
your current revenue at 900 million dollars annually but that is projected to
grow to over 2 billion dollars in 25 years for what RTD is currently
projecting to collect in sales tax so that mapping of the escalating cost and
state of good repair against the available revenue sources was
cornerstone to the work in the March 1st report thank you director director
Nicholson thank you excuse me thank you so I have a couple of questions that the
first one and I promise slightly more fun question than my my last one what
when we talk about three trains a day what kind of hours are we talking about
here because I've heard lots of different sort of understandings of like
what could I use this for and you know if you're running a train back from
Denver to Boulder at 5 p.m. you know you can use that for a meeting in the middle
of the day you can use that for 6 p.m. or 6 30 you can use that for commuting you
can't use that to go to a Nuggets game for example and so maybe you can help me
think about and help the public what kinds of travel is this gonna serve and
what kinds of stuff because again it's only three trains a day is it gonna be
outside of and also are we talking about three trains a day five seven days a
week or only five days a week am I gonna be able to take this down to pride for
example if we're running and do that or is it would it only be running weekday
service thanks and then I'll have I have follow-ups so sure I don't know the
schedule that was a part of the RTC modeling off the top of my head but we
can certainly pull that and have that a part of the June presentation if you so
desire but it was for seven days a week and it did adjust for weekend patterns
versus weekday I just don't know the exact times off the top my head appreciate
it yeah that would be super helpful because my when I've gotten good
questions about this my constituents have asked what am I going to be able to
use it for if I'm in Denver what am I able to do the same thing I'm bolder
second question so we got a fairly sobering I think is the right word
presentation from our asset management team at our training I'm a fellow
relatively new director so we get a bunch of different meetings where they
explain different stuff to us and part of that training was over just how
freaking expensive it is to manage something like a fixed rail asset over
the course of multiple decades and how you really have to think about these
things not in terms of what it's gonna cost for five years or ten years but
twenty thirty and then to replace all of it when we get there and hilariously
enough in an article I think about sound transit to later that day I came across
this wonderful quote but from Willie Brown who is the former speaker of the
California State Assembly where I grew up in the former mayor of San Francisco
in a candid admission of how the political world operates Willie Brown
the former mayor of San Francisco once dismissed the cost overruns on a
transportation hub intended for the bullet train in the world of civic
projects the first budget is really just a down payment he wrote in a guest
newspaper column in 2013 if people knew the real costs from the start nothing
would ever get approved the idea is to get going start digging a hole and make
it so big there's no alternative to coming up with the money to fill it in
isn't that what joint service starter service kind of is thank you I'm asking
that as a question I mean no because we have a cost estimate through 2050 that
was showed to you in the first presentation and map the revenue sources
to the projected cost so I certainly wouldn't characterize it that way I'll
just ask one quick follow-up is that's okay given the significant routine cost
overruns as director O'Keeffe alluded to that for example high-speed rail in
California has undergone where the project has turned out to be billions
more expensive than it initially cost given that we see this in public
projects everywhere what makes you confident as someone who has worked on
these things and been in government for a long time what makes you confident
that you're right this time when so often other people get this wrong I think
the projects that we are looking at from a rail perspective is very different
than high-speed rail I mean I don't even think it's like an apple to a pineapple
because yeah it's it's not the same species really because what we are
talking about is utilizing underutilized current infrastructure in the state of
Colorado and what we have seen is an opportunity that exists right now that
even is different than when fast tracks passed in 04 when fast tracks passed in
04 there was a lot more free operations on this line than exists today the NSF
has shifted a lot of their freight operations to the Greeley sub and out
east and that has created this opportunity to utilize an existing
infrastructure asset for a new purpose as we're no for it was in war and
conflict with their freight operations than it is today same thing with
mountain rail we have an opportunity to use an existing asset that is under
utilized because of the coal plant closures and Craig and Hayden has
created this capacity on the line the lines in good shape it's active today
still moving coal but it's about to be inactive for half of the segment when
those coal plants close in 29 and so it's really taking a sunk cost from an
infrastructure perspective and repurposing it for a future need is how
I would see these projects and I think what's different about the way we've
approached this and that we've had success with with at least Union Pacific
in the mountain rail access agreement is having an enumerated infrastructure list
that corresponds with the actual daily round trips so the way that access
agreement reads is for these daily round trips three of them here's the actual
infrastructure that is needed to empower that on this timeline and certainly if
that infrastructure list is priced out 20 years from now the escalation cost is
going to be different but we have plans to do those infrastructure projects this
calendar year so we believe our cost estimates are good I don't think anything
is ever bulletproof but I think that the benefit to the state of Colorado that we
would get from these projects of taking cars off the road and driving better
land use decisions where we have housing in fill to get to a smart growth
strategy for the state of Colorado is worthy of the cause and I think we have
paved a much different way than what California has done and certainly I
think we are all students of having watched what California has done and
paved a different way forward in Colorado that has as much certainty
around it as you possibly can for a big public infrastructure project thank you
I'm gonna go to director Peculary I saw his hand and I'll come back to you
secretary thank you chair thank you guests for your presentation appreciate
it I think I just want to start out by saying the front-range needs rail needs
passenger rail service we have a growing population people moving here and
bringing their cars we have increased poor air quality there's a lot of
reasons why we need rail and there's so many reasons that in 2003 the people
said we need rail and they asked for it and time and time again people have
asked for it over and over again and the legislator even this year said once
again we need rail RTD you have to build the rail that you promised to build back
from the voters said you had to build rail so I'd like to keep to our
commitment towards at least doing what we can to finish fast tracks because we
need rail but I do have a little bit of a few concerns and I think I'll just
highlight one concern and a question first and then a concern I guess they're
tied together but three strong trips per day is starter service it's useful
transit for some but not as many as ten round trips or twelve I'd really like to
see the movement towards double tracking so we can get those higher frequencies
and make this a really useful transit service for the people along the front
range in the front range district but with what we're building and what we're
committing what this IGA first of all is just allowing something to go forward so
we can get more information we're not committing any funds yet so I do hope
you support the IGA but in the idea I would like to see some type of assurance
that we can continue on the path towards that those ten twelve round trips per
day or double tracking and if it's possible the legislators already given
FRPRD and a revenue for collecting revenue I don't really see in the future
of the state giving us a couple billion dollars to build double track front
range passenger rail but the people could choose to do it so I would like I
guess my question then to not lead a sorry about the leading question is if
it would be possible to do put some assurances in that would require this
new entity with IGA to pursue expanded service and not just stop at three
trains per day thank you thanks yeah and I think that's important feedback as to
what the board would like in the IGA and so we could certainly take that back
thank you thank you director all right any further comments questions
secretary and then director Guzman thank you two very quick things so first
off I just want to make an important point I want this train I actually
really really want this train I am one of a handful of people on the board who
doesn't have a car getting to Boulder getting to Longmont this would be and I
live like 10 minutes from Union Station this would be a massive improvement in
my quality of life getting up to getting up the northwest and for exactly the
reason that you alluded to miss Kaufman this is an opportunity to build a ton of
new housing in a place that badly needs it make it easier for people to get to
Denver there are lots of reasons in principle to like this project the same
way that I like the idea of having a summer home in Bali or a winter home the
question is can I afford it and can I make it can I make it work can I can do
it as the access of me flying out there you know so really it just comes down to
I'm putting you through the paces on this I'm running the traps I'm making this as
difficult as I am because as someone who's been involved in government since
I was 18 I am terrified genuinely freaked at you know have had mild panic
attacks over this decision because I don't want to turn 50 or 55 or 60 and
look back and say wow I signed on to a gigantic money pit on the other hand I
don't want to look back and say wow I missed out on signing on to one of the
best expansions of passenger rail that we were ever going to have so it doesn't
come from a place of disliking the project it comes from a place of
gigantic amounts of fear over the significance of this decision yeah I
appreciate that I think it's really well found it given the history of this
project and the way we've grown as a metro area and the needs that we have in
a metro area for more transit and rail and the constraints that we have around
revenue as a state and how we can gain new revenue as a state so I think all of
that thoughtful approach is warranted which is partly why you know the step
that we are contemplating now is can we all agree on how we would make joint
decisions to then go negotiate with BNSF come back to the governing boards with
the results of that and say is this ROI worth it and that would come after a
successful negotiation that would enumerate the infrastructures that has
to correspond with the access agreement for daily round trips and at that
juncture I think you would have a big decision to be made and we would have a
lot more information on we have verified the infrastructure list with BNSF we
have you know the engineers price that out and then we have a financial model
on how it would work right so you know does it make sense for CTIO who has
bonding capacity to finance all of PTC that would be enumerated in the finance
plan like how which piece of which puzzle would look at the finance plan
based off of that infrastructure list obviously RTD would need to look at just
infrastructure costs within the RTD region not outside of it so you know I
think we're you know attempting to eat an elephant we have to do it chunk by
chunk here and it's really getting to a place where we all agree on how we're
gonna operate together to collaborate to get to an access agreement and then once
we have an access agreement how do we create a finance plan based off of that
agreement and then you all will have a big decision to be made on the ROI of
that investment we just can't get there without having those negotiations first
thank you based on the sake of time I'm gonna have treasure banker and then
director Guzman as our final two thank you you know one of the things we
haven't really talked about and I was hoping that we could get to it in in our
executive session but time is going by fast well we can extend also and start
our board meeting lead teams I've been trying to meet with as many of our board
directors as possible and I'm hoping to meet with everybody I've been working I
think you all know I've been working on these numbers for a long time but last
year the state legislature gave us two new revenue sources so when we're
talking about oh my this project looks first of all cost estimates we're
getting right now are very reasonable much less than what they were even a
couple of years ago but we now have some new revenue sources out there and
actually I was hoping Lisa wasn't going to hear me do something some of this but
if you go in and you take a look at the two new bills that were passed last year
and the different pots of money that they put the money in we have or the
state has a hundred and seventy four million dollars a year of new money that
we need to ask for and write a grant for so if you're talking about RTD money
this could be RTD money sorry Lisa but this is where we need to talk with the
state we need to do some negotiation and when we're talking about how it's going
to hurt our budget this is all new this is all new money a hundred and seventy
four million dollars the state legislature gave us last year for
transit now is it all RTD no probably not chunk of it could be a big chunk of
that could be and this is where I was hoping as a board that we could talk
about this because again it's we can debate Pfizer and we will we should and
there's a lot of things that we can talk about with Pfizer but there's so much
new money on the table there's so much opportunity and we've got some great
partners here to make it happen and so if we do go into special session you know
go ahead and pass out my my last Excel spreadsheet here I keep making tweaks to
it I will continue to do it but I guess I just didn't want the board to think
that it's going to be coming mostly or coming out of our base budget because it
doesn't have to it could come out of the new money that the state legislature has
opened up for us so the treasurer can I say one thing on that is it's also not
just the last two bills that passed and actually if you go back and you look at
Senate bill 260 that passed in 2021 one of the things that we created and that
was the new day was the new delivery fee and the delivery fee was created in
order to help public agencies that need to reflate to low to zero emissions and
it created around 60 million dollars in the first five years so it's that 29
cents that shows up on your Amazon bill every time you get Amazon and that you
know we would love to partner with RTD on their refleeting strategy obviously
refleeting for air quality improvements is a big priority for us and so it's not
just on these rail projects do we want to be a collaborative funding partner
it's really on all the needs that RTD has as we try to reach our mutual goals
around expanding transit and rail service for the metro area and so not
just the rail projects is important for you to hear me say there's all sorts of
money that we have created to partner with RTD on that we want to partner with
RTD on and really think about how we maximize public financing tools that we
have at the state in order to get to our broader vision of a smart growth
strategy for the state of Colorado thank you director Guzman thank you mr. chair
I also want to see this project get done I voted for it when it was first in
front of me on a ballot when I was early voting as a young child right like let's
be real okay well yeah okay it feels a long time ago now so I get the
frustration of all of my long monsters who have been emailing me lovingly about
trying to approve something that we're actually not making a decision on right
now but I do understand the frustration and consternation and I don't want to be
burnt in effigy and Longmont by anybody okay I represent Denver and my concern
as a director needs to be to my sub-district first and then to the
benefit of the entire region I appreciate the outreach for partnership
from the state that's the first time I've heard it given to us that way and
explained to us that way and I would like to do that partnership as well but I am
hesitant to reach my hand out in return when every time I turn around I'm
attacked or the board is attacked or the agency is attacked by the state and so
from me to the administration of our state right now I would really
appreciate it if you guys would work with us so that we can have a better
relationship because right now I am once bitten and twice shy which puts me in a
defensive mode over my agency as is my fiduciary duty of loyalty my question
though is for our missing partner who is not I believe represented here but when
is FRPRD gonna get there taxing situation in order and go to the
voters because we can do a lot within the regional transportation district
geography beyond that I wouldn't vote to commit any money outside of it and I
don't believe we are legally allowed to do so there was some change in the law
but I still didn't understand whether that allowed us to do that or not and so
just a final question that can come back later in the report next month what's
going on with our partner that is absent at this point because their funding has
come from the state and not from their own resources thanks yeah it's a great
question and it's partly why we have kind of jumped into the fray to start
trying to figure out how to create this collaborative approach to funding these
projects and and again why I think it's important for you to hear me say it's
not just about funding Northwest rails commitment to the voters but it's about
completion of all the unfinished fast-tracks projects because we have
pulled multiple times front-range passenger rail and it is not currently
viable at the ballot because of the voters skepticism that they we all
collectively could be trusted with a new revenue source to do a rail project
because of the hangover of fast-tracks and so you know it's a big barrier to
going back to the voters and asking for increased resources is that they don't
have an answer to this outstanding problem and so I think it's incumbent on
everyone who is trying to provide the best transit service and expand its
service for Colorado to try to see how we problem-solve around that because
it's not just FRPR that is suffering from it it will be the case if RTD needs
to go back to the voters for new transit money it will be the case if there's new
RTAs in the metro area that would like to stand up service is that this is a big
barrier to voters approving any additional resources. Thank you. Director
Arisha. Thank You Mr. Chair um I my ears perked up when I heard polling and I
have not seen the polling that was just referenced and so I was wondering if if
that's something that's available or it could be shared um I think that would be
helpful for the board thank you thank you sure I'm happy to share the slide
deck that I did to Colorado rails meeting a couple weekends ago that has
some of those pertinent slides in it well miss Barrett miss Kaufman do you
want to greatly appreciate you for your time thank you directors for comments
and questions we're looking forward to our June report and hopefully the
feedback and questions that were presented this evening will be helpful
going forward so I want to thank you both thank you
all right in a moment the board will meet an executive session regarding a
proposed intergovernmental agreement related to joint service for the
Northwest rail corridor I'd like to amend the emotion to move into executive
session to state that the special board meeting will be during deemed adjourned
after it adjourns into the executive session for public transparency this
means that once the board moves into executive session the main meeting will
be adjourned for anyone who might be in the room or remote the regular scheduled
board meeting will occur after this meeting with the anticipated start time
of I'm gonna say 630 it might be a little bit longer but anticipated start
time of 630 so please know that we'll be back then I'll now entertain a motion to
move into executive session to discuss the following so into 24 six step these
24 - 6 - 4 0 2 4 e for determining positions relative to matter that may be
subject to negotiations developing strategy strategy for negotiations
instructing negotiators and 24 - 6 - 4 0 2 4 B for legal advice regarding proposed
intergovernment agreement and joint service for the Northwest rail corridor
do I have a mover so moved Nicholson do I have a second second okay I'm gonna go
with director Peggy Larry thank you all right for all those who are expected to
attend would you please stay seated yes oh excuse me are there any no votes
seeing none that'll pass 14 0 and 1 absent all right all right for those
expected 10 would you please stay seated and for everyone else would you please
vacate the room at this time and take all your belongings with you thank you